Preliminary Inventory to the Nicolae Petrescu-Comnen Papers, 1917-1958
Hoover Institution Archives
Nicolae Petrescu-Comnen Papers,
1917-1958
80034
Petrescu-Comnen, Nicolae, 1881-1958
22 manuscript boxes (8.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, reports, diplomatic dispatches, clippings, and serial issues, relating to Romanian foreign relations, especially with Germany, Switzerland, and the Vatican; the League of Nations; World War II refugees and relief work; and postwar Romanian émigré life.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Catholic Church--Relations (diplomatic) with Romania.; League of Nations.; International relief.; Refugees.; Romanians in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--Romania.; Germany.; Germany--Foreign relations--Romania.; Romania.; Romania--Foreign relations.; Romania--Foreign relations--Catholic Church.; Romania--Foreign relations--Germany.; Romania--Foreign relations--Switzerland.; Switzerland.; Switzerland--Foreign relations--Romania.; Diplomats--Romania.
Biography
Romanian diplomat; delegate to the League of Nations, 1923-1928 and 1938; ambassador to Germany, 1927-1929 and 1932; minister of foreign affairs, 1938.
Container List
Nos. 3,6,13,14,32, 68, P-6, and P-7 were not received by the Hoover Institution
- 1. Garda de Fier (Box 1.)
- 2. Diplomatic Cables, Berlin, 1937-38
- 4. Letters while in Berlin, 1928-30 and 1936-38: includes letters from Goring, Ribbentrop, Carol II
- 5. Conclusion of a book, in manuscript, pp. 451-90
- 7. Red Cross file, 1942-43; also NPC visa extensions while in Italy during the war; few other minor items
- 8. Red Cross file, 1942: attempts to help Romanian prisoners in the USSR: includes letters with Mihai Antonescu
- 9. Red Cross file, 1944: includes letters with Corsini (Box 2.)
- 10. Red Cross file, 1945-47: letters with Sforza, Vatican, Vintila Horia, Grigorcea
- 11. Red Cross file, 1948-51: refugee problems
- 12. Red Cross file, 1948-51: refugee problems
- 15. Newspaper clippings: Ankara Conference, II.38; Geneva sessions, 1938 (incl. Jewish problem); Beck visit to Romania, X.38; Carol II visit to England, XI.38 (Box 3.)
- 16. Butenko Affair, 1938
- 17. Berlin documents, 1928-38: letters and newspapers, no cables; two manuscripts on My Missions to Berlin, II.28-III.30 and VI.32-II.38 and on Missed Occasion for Entente with the Soviets, 1928 (Box 4.)
- 18. Diplomatic Cables, 1938: Czech crisis and Carol II visit to Berchstesgaden especially covered
- 19. Manuscripts on wartime visitors: Gigurtu, 1941; Prince Nicolae, 1941; Queen Helen, 1943; Queen Marie, 1942
- 20. Correspondence with Romanian National Committee and Royal Family, especially concerning financing of the Romanian National Committee, 1940's-1950's (Box 5.)
- 21. Reports and Diplomatic Cables, Geneva, 1938: includes talks with Litvinov
- 22. Reports and Diplomatic Cables, 1938: concerning relations and talks with Hungary
- 23. Reports and Diplomatic Cables, 1938: concerning Minorities Treaty, Little Entente, and Hungary
- 24. Reports and Diplomatic Cables while Foreign Minister, last half of 1938
- 25. Reports while Foreign Minister, late 1938: concerning minorities, Munich, relations with the USSR (Box 6.)
- 26. Reports, cables, and instructions, Berlin, 1934-35
- 26a. Reports, cables, and instructions, Berlin, 1934-35: documents in this file are marked in NPC wartime code for identification
- 27. Minorities Question: planning documents for minorities commissariat, press clippings
- 28. Mimeographed records of Council of League of Nations, V.38
- 29. Reports and Diplomatic Cables, Vatican, 1939-40 (Box 7.)
- 30. Reports and Diplomatic Cables, Vatican, 1931-32
- 31. Correspondence with Royal Family: Prince Nicolae, 1957; Hohenzollern-Sigmaringen on Zizi Lambrino, 1957
- 33. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950's: many very interesting pieces
- 34. Right of Existence for Small Nations--English translation of NPC work (Box 8.)
- 35. File on NPC Early Career: Durostor, 1920-22; decorations, postwar papers, translation of some articles
- 36. Miscellaneous Press Clippings, 1930-40; also Tatarescu memorandum on Groza Government
- 37. Postwar Correspondence: refugees, personal relations, some on publications, late-1940's to 1950's (Box 9.)
- 38. Ethnographic Maps and Materials on Romania, 1938-40
- 39. Documents and Cables, Mission to Berne, Switzerland, 1924-25: including visit of King Ferdinand (Box 10.)
- 40. Documents and Letters, Berne, 1923-28; also congratulatory letters on appointment to Berlin
- 41. Foreign Ministry document opposing treaty revision in Bessarabia, Bukovina, Transylvania; ethnographic maps of Romania; Notiziario Romeno
- 42. Miscellaneous letters, 1923-1940: reflect career, but not related to foreign policy
- 43. Newspaper clippings, 1932, 1935, 1937, especially concerning relations with Germany and the USSR (Box 11.)
- 44. Berne, 1917-1919: Romania in World War I, NPC propaganda activity for Romania Mare
- 45. Cables and letters to NPC as Foreign Minister: relate especially to Rome and Paris
- 46. Letters and Diplomatic Cables, Vatican, 1939-40
- 46a. Reports, Cables, and Instructions, Vatican, 1939-40: documents in this file are marked with NPC wartime code for identification; many relate to Germany (Box 12.)
- 47. Letters, 1938, congratulating NPC on new post; also, 1931 negotiations with Vatican concerning marriage of Princess Ileana
- 48. Press clippings on 1938 Salonika Accord
- 49. File of 1938 press clippings and materials on Romanian National Committee
- 50. 1938 press clippings and two reports: 1) on departure from Berlin, and 2) on meeting with Filderman
- 51. (14 51a and 51b) Press Clippings on Carol II visit to London, XI.38 (Box 13.)
- 52. Press clippings, 1938: Carol II in England; Beck at Galati
- 53. Typed manuscript for Ombres et Poussieres, in French
- 54. Typed manuscript for Ombres et Poussieres, in English (Box 14.)
- 55. Typed manuscript for Dust and Shadows, in English
- 56. Typed manuscript for Firenze Citta Aperta, in French
- 57. Letters of NPC related to preparation and publication of Firenze Citta Aperta (Box 15.)
- 58. Letters, Correspondence, Clippings, and Reviews of I Responsabili: letters to participants on Munich crisis are especially important
- 59. Press comments and letters of appreciation concerning I Responsabili: includes letters from Adenauer and Francois-Poncet (Box 16.)
- 60. Correspondence relating to Preluddi
- 61. Romanian Relief Committee in Italy: letters and comments on some of NPC articles; NPC and Mihai I comments on deaths of Dinu Bratianu and Maniu; Also sprach Litvinov manuscript
- 62. Correspondence, comments on publications, 1950's: includes letter from Adenauer
- 63. Miscellaneous letters, 1952-56: relate to variety of subjects, including exiles, publication of articles, some responses from US government officials in response to NPC articles (Box 17.)
- 64. Various manuscripts: Pour une amitie hungaro-roumaine; Litvinov; Roumanie devant la conference de la paix; A quel moment l'Italie lia-t-elle son sort a celui de l'Allemagne?; interesting letter concerning Titulescu; Our Foreign Policy by Gheorghe Tatarescu
- 65. Working papers for Amitie hungaro-roumaine, Dust and Shadows, etc.; some exile publications; 1944-46 correspondence concerning publications; R.A. Comnene letters
- 66. R.A. Comnene letters with NPC, 1954-55, Lotissements in Brazil (Box 18.)
- 67. NPC letters concerning public activities and publications, 1940's-1950's
- 69. 1945-46 letters related to Anarchy, Tyranny, or International Organization and Pour eviter une troisieme grande guerre; also letters with military missions in Italy and letter to Vichinsky, 1946
- 70. Visit to Brazil, 1954
- 71. Visit to Spain and Brazil: letters, clippings, menus, etc. (Box 19.)
- 72. Visit to Brazil, 1955: newspaper clippings, letters, visit cards
- 73. Papers related to NPC and Titulescu visit to Berlin, speech texts; also some postwar correspondence
- 74. Letters to wife, late 1940's; also, article on map of Vatican
- 75. Rome speech, 1950: letters and press comments, visit cards
- 76. Correspondence, 1957: related to Luci e Ombre and I Responsabili (Box 20.)
- 77. Press comments and correspondence, 1945-46: concerns Suggerimenti per la pace and Anarchie, Dictature, ou organisation internationale
- 78. Newspaper clippings with mentions of NPC, 1946
- 79. Mission to Berne, 1917 (Box 21.)
- 80. Letters with Romanians, especially Mircea Popescu, 1954
- 81. Letters, 1954-55
- 82. Advertisements for various books by NPC
- 83. Negotiations with publishers concerning NPC books, especially with Bompiani
- 84. Correspondence related to French version of I Responsabili
- 85. Correspondence concerning articles and books, 1955-56
- 86. Note on Minorities, 1944; 1957 correspondence with G. Uscatescu; other miscellaneous correspondence
- 87. Typed manuscript of second half of Preluddi (Box 22.)
- 88. Correspondence with Romanian Library of Freiburg
- 89. Correspondence with Societatea Academica Romana, 1958: especially with Barlea and Mircea Popescu; arrangements for publication by the Academia of Un point d'histoire vecu
- 90. Letters concerning Prima experienta comunista in Ungaria
- P-2. Mission to Berne, 1919: also Lausanne, Paris during World War I
- 86a. Correspondence concerning publication of books, including I Responsabili and Preluddi, 1949-52.